<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Kings Maiesties answer to a late petition presented unto him by the hands of Mr. Alexander Henderson, from the commissioners of the Generall Assemblie of the Kirk of Scotland with their humble remonstrance and renewed petition to the Kings Most Excellent Majestie, from their meeting at Edinburgh, June 2, 1643.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2098</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35826</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15564564</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15564564</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103790</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103790)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1184:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Kings Maiesties answer to a late petition presented unto him by the hands of Mr. Alexander Henderson, from the commissioners of the Generall Assemblie of the Kirk of Scotland with their humble remonstrance and renewed petition to the Kings Most Excellent Majestie, from their meeting at Edinburgh, June 2, 1643.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
                  <author>Ker, A.</author>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Bryson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, the humble remonstrance and renewed petition of the commissioners ... " (p. 13-30) signed: A. Ker.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103790:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE KINGS MAIESTIES ANSWER, To a late Petition preſented unto him by the hands of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ALEXANDER HENDERSON, from the COMMISSIONERS of the Generall ASSEMBLIE of the Kirk of SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>WITH Their humble REMONSTRANCE and renewed PETITION to the Kings moſt Excellent MAjESTIE, from their meeting at EDINBURGH, June 2. 1643.</p>
            <p>EDINBURGH, Printed by ROBERT BRYSON. 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:103790:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103790:2"/>
            <head>His Majeſties Anſvver to a late Petition preſented unto him by the hands of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ALEXANDER HENDERSON, from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the generall Aſſemblie of the Church of SCOTLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E received lately a Petition from you, by the hands of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Alexander Henderſon,</hi> To the which we intended to have given an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, as ſoon as we had tranſacted the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with the other Commiſſioners addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to us from the Conſervators of the Treatie of that our Kingdome. But finding the ſame to be publiſhed in Print, and to bee diſperſed throughout Our Kingdome, to the great danger of Scandalling of Our well-affected Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who may interpret the bitterneſſe and ſharpneſſe of ſome expreſſions not to be ſo agreeable to that regard and reverence which is due to our Perſon, and the matter it ſelf to be reproachfull to the honour and conſtitution of this Kingdome, we have been compelled the more ſtrictly to examine as well the Authority of the Petitioners, as the matter of the petition it ſelf, and to publiſh our opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of both, that our Subjects of both Kingdomes may ſee how equally, juſt, and ſenſible we are of the Laws and honour of both Our Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>And firſt, upon peruſall of the Petition, We required to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103790:3"/>ſee the Commiſſion by which the meſſenger who brought this Petition, or the perſons who ſent him, are qualified to intermedle in Affairs ſo forraigne to their juriſdiction, and of ſo great concernement to this our Kingdome of England. Upon examination whereof, and in defence of the Laws and Government of this our Kingdome, which we are truſted and ſworne to defend, Wee muſt profeſſe that the Petitioners, or the generall Aſſembly of Our Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> have not the leaſt Authority or power to intermeddle or interpoſe in the affaires of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or Church, which are ſetled and eſtabliſhed by the proper laws of this Land, and till they bee altered by the ſame competent power, cannot be enveighed againſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a due ſenſe of Us and this Nation, much leſſe can they preſent any advice or declaration to Our Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament againſt the ſame, or to that purpoſe to ſend any letters, as they have now done, to any Miniſter of Our Church here, who by the Lawes of this land cannot cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond againſt the ſame. Therefore wee do believe that the Petitioners, when they ſhall conſider how unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it is by the Laws of that Kingdome, and how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary it is to the Laws of this, to the profeſsions they have made to each other, and how unbecomming in it ſelf for them to require the ancient, happie and eſtabliſhed government of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to bee altered, and conformed to the lawes and conſtitutions of another Church, will find themſelves miſled by the information of ſome factious perſons here, who would willingly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the Petitioners to foment a difference and diviſion between the two Kingdomes, which wee have with ſo much care and induſtry endeavoured to prevent, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving labour'd more to quench the combuſtion in this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103790:3"/>Kingdom, then we have to hinder the like from either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring <hi>Ireland,</hi> or entring into <hi>Scotland,</hi> which if all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will equally labour, will undoubtedly bee avoided. But we cannot ſo eaſily paſſe over the mention of <hi>Ireland,</hi> being mov'd to it by ſcandalous aſperſions, that have bin often caſt upon us upon that ſubject, and the uſe that hath been made of the wofull diſtractions of that Kingdome, as of a Seminary of feares and jealouſies to beget the like diſtraction in this, and (which leſt they may have farther influence) Wee are the more willing to make Our inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence appeare in that particular.</p>
            <p>When firſt that horrid Rebellion began, Wee were in Our Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the ſenſe we had then of it, the expreſſions we made concerning it, the Commiſſions (together with ſome other aſſiſtance) we ſent immediatly into that Kingdome, and the inſtant Recommendation we made of it to both Our Houſes of Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> are knowne to all perſons of quality there and then about Us. After Our returne into <hi>England,</hi> Our ready concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to all the deſires of both Houſes that might moſt ſpeedily repreſſe that horrible Rebellion, by paſſing the Bill of preſſing, &amp; in it a clauſe which quitted a right chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged by all, and enjoyed by many of Our Predeceſſors, by parting with Our Rights in the lands eſcheated to Us by that rebellion, for the encouragement of adventures, by emptying of Our Magazines of Armes and Ammunition for that ſervice (which we have ſince needed for our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary defence and preſervation) by conſenting to all Bills for the raiſing of money for the ſame, though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining unuſuall clauſes, which truſted both Houſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Us with the matter of diſpoſing it, Our often preſſing both Houſes, not to neglect that Kingdome, by being
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103790:4"/>diverted by conſiderations and diſputes leſſe concerning both Kingdomes, Our offer of raiſing 10000. Voluntiers to be ſent thither, and Our ſeverall Offers to engage Our owne Royall perſon in the ſuppreſſion of that horrid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion are no leſſe known to all this Nation, then Our perpetuall earneſtneſſe by our Forraigne Miniſters to keep all manner of ſupplies from being tranſported for the relief of the Rebels, is knowne to ſeverall neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Princes. VVhich if all Our Subjects will conſider, and withall how many of the men, and how much of the money raiſed for that end, and how much time, care, and induſtrie have been diverted from that employment, and employed in this unnaturall warre againſt Us, (the true cauſe of the preſent miſerie and want which Our Brittiſh armies there do now endure) they will ſoone free us from all thoſe imputations ſo ſcandalouſly and groundleſly laid upon us, and impute the continuance of the Combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of that miſerable Kingdome, the danger it may bring upon our Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the beginning of this dolefull deſolation, to thoſe who are truely guilty of it.</p>
            <p>For unitie in Religion: which is deſired, We cannot but anſwer, That wee much apprehend leſt the Papiſts may make ſome advantage of that expreſſion, by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing that ſcandall with more authoritie, which they have ever heretofore uſed to caſt upon the Reformation, by interpreting all the differences in Ceremonie, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or indifferent opinions between ſeverall Proteſtant Churches, to bee differences in Religion; And leſt our good ſubjects of <hi>England,</hi> who have ever eſteemed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the ſame Religion with you, ſhould ſuſpect themſelves to bee eſteemed by you to be of a contrary.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103790:4"/>And that religion which they and their anceſtors have held ever ſince the bleſſed reformation, and in and for which they are reſolved to dye, is taxed and branded of falſehood or inſufficiency, by ſuch a deſire.</p>
            <p>For uniformity in Church Government, We conceived the anſwer formerly given by us to the former petition in this argument, would have ſatisfied the petitioners, and is ſo full, that we can adde little to it. <hi>viZ. That the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment here eſtabliſhed by the lawes, hath ſo neare a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and intermixture with the Civill State (which may be unknown to the petitioners) that til a compoſed diſgeſted form be preſented to us, upon a free debate of both Houſes in a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary way, whereby the conſert and approbation of this whole Kingdom may be had, and We and all our ſubjects may diſcerne, what is to be left in, or brought in, as well as what is to be taken away, We know not how to conſent to any alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, other wiſe then to ſuch an act for the eaſe of tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in the matter of Ceremonies, as We have often offered and that this, and any thing elſe that may concerne the peace of the Church, and the advancement of Gods true Religion may be ſoberly diſcuſſed, and happily effected, We have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly offered, and are ſtill willing that debates of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be entered into by a Syned of godly and learned Divines, to be regularly choſen according to the Laws and Cuſtomes of this Kingdome. To which we ſhall bee willing that ſome learned Divines of our Church of Scotland be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſent, to be preſent and offer and debate their Reaſons.</hi> With this anſwer the petitioners had great reaſon to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce without enlarging the matter of their former pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition only with bitter expreſſions againſt the eſtabliſhed government and laws of their neighbour Nation, (as if it were contrary to the word of God) with whom they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103790:5"/>have ſo lately entred into a ſtrict amity and friendſhip.</p>
            <p>But we cannot enough wonder, that the petitioners ſhould interpoſe themſelves, not only as fit directors and judges betwen Us and Our two Houſes of Parliament, in buſineſſe ſo wholly concerning the peace and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this our kingdome, and in a matter ſo abſolutely entruſted to us, as what new laws to conſent or not to conſent to, But ſhould aſſume and publiſh, That the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of reformation in this kingdome is in a peaceable and Parliamentary way, When all the world may know, That the proceedings here, have bene and are not only contrary to all the rules and precedents of former Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments, but deſtructive to the freedome, priviledge, and dignity of Parliaments themſelves: that wee were firſt driven by tumults, for the ſafety of our life, from our cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and have bene ſince pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, fought withall, and are now kept from thence by an army rayſed, as is pretended, by the two Houſes, which conſiſt not of the fourth part of the number they ought to do, the reſt being either driven from thence by the ſame violence, or expell'd or impriſoned for not conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the treaſons and unheard of Inſolencies practiſed againſt us, And if the petitioners could beleeve theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings to be in a peaceable Parliamentary way, they were very unacquainted with the order and conſtitution of this Kingdome, and not ſo fit inſtruments to promote that reformation and peace: they ſeeme to deſire.</p>
            <p>We cannot beleeve the intermixture of the preſent Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall government with the Civill State, to be other then a very good reaſon, and that the governement of the Church ſhould be by the rules of humane policy, to be other then a very good rule, unleſſe ſome other govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103790:5"/>were as well proved as pretended to be better war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by God.</p>
            <p>Of any bills offerd us for reformation, we ſhall not now ſpeak, they being a part of thoſe articles upon which we have offered and expect to treats but cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by what authority you prejudge our judgement here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, by denouncing Gods anger upon us, and our hazard of the loſſe of the hearts of all our good Subjects, if we conſent not unto them. The influence of ſo many bleſſings from heaven upon the reignes of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and our father of bleſsed memory, and the acknowledgement of them by all Proteſtant Churches to have been carefull nurſes to the Church of Chriſt and to have excellentlie diſcharged their duties in the cuſtody and vindication of religion, and the affection of their Subjects to them, do ſufficiently aſsure Us, that we ſhould neither ſtop the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of ſuch bleſſings, nor grieve the hearts of all the godly, nor hazard the loſſe of the hearts of our good Subjects, although we ſtill maintaine in this Kingdome the ſame eſtabliſht Eccleſiaſticall government, which flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht in their times, and under their ſpeciall protection.</p>
            <p>We doubt not but our Subjects of Scotland will reſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly ſatisfied with ſuch alterations in their owne Church as we have aſſented unto, and not bee perſwaded by a meer aſſertion, that there is no hope of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of what is there ſetled by law, unleſſe that bee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe altered which is ſetled here, And our Subjects of England will never depart from their dutifull affection to Us, for not conſenting to new laws, which by the law of the land, they know, We may as juſtly reject if we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove not of them, as either houſe hath power to prepare for, or both to propound to us. Nor are you a little mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103790:6"/>if either you beleeve the generality of this Nation to deſire a change of Church-government, or that moſt of thoſe who deſire it, deſire by it to introduce that which you onely eſteeme a reformation, but are as unwilling to what you call the yoke of Chriſt and obedience to the Goſpell, as thoſe whom you call prophane and worldly men, and ſo equally averſe both to Epiſcopacy and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie, that if they ſhould prevaile in this particular, the abolition of the one would be no inlet to the other, nor would your hearts bee leſſe grieved, your expectations leſſe fruſtrated, your hopes leſſe aſhamed, or your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation more ſecured. And the petitioners, upon due conſideration, will not finde themſelves leſſe miſtaken in the government of all the reformed Churches, which they ſay is by Aſſemblies, then they are in the beſt way of a reformation, which ſure is beſt to be in a common and ordinary way, where the paſſion or intereſt of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular men may not impoſe upon the publique, but altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be then onely made, when, upon calmed debates, and evident and cleare Reaſon and convenience, the ſame ſhall be generally conſented to for the peace and ſecurity of the people, and thoſe who are truſted by the Law with ſuch debates, are not diveſted of that truſt upon a generall charge of corruptions pretended to have entred by that way, and of being the perſons to be reformed, and ſo unfit to bee Reformers And certainly the like Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick with the like charges and pretences might be uſed to make the Parliament it ſelf an incapable Judge of any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation either in Church or State.</p>
            <p>For the generall expreſſions in the Petition againſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, in which the petitioners may bee underſtood to charge Us with complyance and favour even to their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, Wee have taken all occaſion to publiſh to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103790:6"/>world Our practice and reſolution in the true proteſtant Reformed Religion, and wee are verily perſwaded there is no one Subject in either of our Dominions, who at all knowes Us, and hath obſerved our Life; but is in his ſoul ſatisfied of our Zeal and unremoveable Affection to that Religion, and of our true diſlike of, and hearty opoſition to popery, And as wee willingly conſented, at our being in Scotland, to all acts propoſed to Us, for the diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing and Reforming the Papiſts in that our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo by our Proclamations for the putting of all Lawes ſeverally in execution againſt Recuſants, and by not refuſing any one Bill preſented to Us to that purpoſe in this Kingdome, and by our perpetuall and publique profeſſions of Readineſſe with the advice of Our two Houſes of Parliament prepared for Us in a deliberate and orderly way, to finde ſome expedition to perfect ſo good a worke, or conceived wee had not left it poſſible for any man to believe Us guilty of tolerating any part of the Romiſh Tyrannie or Superſtition, or to ſuſpect that the Converſion of our deareſt Conſort, was not ſo much our deſire, that the Acceſſion of as many Crownes, as God hath already beſtowed upon us, would be more welcome to us then that day: A bleſſing which it is Our daily pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the almighty to beſtow upon Us.</p>
            <p>But we might well have expected from the Petitioners, who have in their ſolemne Nationall Covenant literally ſworne ſo much Care and ſafety of Our Perſon, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but know in how much danger that hath bin and ſtill is by the power and threats of Rebellious Armes, that they would as well have remembred the 23 of October, as the 5 of November, and as well have taken notice of the Army raiſed and led againſt Us by the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:103790:7"/>which hath actually aſſaulted and endeavoured to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Us, which wee know to abound in Browniſts, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, and other ſectaries, and in which we have reaſon (by the priſoners we have taken, and the evidence they have given) to believe there are many more Papiſts (and many of thoſe forraigners) then in all our army, as have adviſed Us to disband out of the army of the Earle of New caſtle, which is raiſed for Our defence, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in that Armie, who are knowne to be no ſuch num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as to endanger their obtaining any power of building their <hi>Babell,</hi> and ſetting up their Idolatrie, and whoſe loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie he hath reaſon to commend (though he was never ſuſpected for favouring their Religion) not before that of Proteſtants, but of ſuch as rebell under that Title; And whoſe aſſiſtance is as due to us by the law of God, &amp; man, to reſcue Us from domeſtick Rebellion, as to defend us from forraigne invaſion, which we think no man denyes to be lawfull for them to do. But we do ſolemnly declare and proteſt, That God ſhall no ſooner free us from the deſperate and rebellious armes taken up againſt Us, but we ſhall endeavour to free our ſelves and King dome from any fear of danger from the other, by diſarming them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the laws of this Land, as we ſhall not faile to ſend our Commiſſioner to the Aſſembly at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for it by the laws of Scotland.</p>
            <p>To conclude, We deſire and require the Petitioners (as becomes good and pious Preachers of the Goſpel) to uſe their utmoſt endeavours to compoſe any diſtraction in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, or miſunderſtandings, which may by the faction of ſome turbulent perſons, bee raiſed in the minds of Our good Subjects of that Our Kingdome, and to infuſe into them a true ſence of Charitie, Obedience, and Humilitie,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103790:7"/>the great principles of Chriſtian Religion; That they may not ſuffer themſelves to bee tranſported with things they do not underſtand, or thinke themſelves concerned in the Government of another Kingdome, becauſe it is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtomes of that in which they live; But that they diſpoſe themſelves with modeſty and devotion to the ſervice of Almighty God, with duty and affection to the obedience of us and our laws (remembring the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Grace, Favour and Benignitie We have alwaies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to that Our Native Kingdome) and with brother-therly and chriſtian charitie one towards another; And Wee doubt not but God in his mercy to Us and them will make us inſtruments of his bleſſings upon each others, and both of us a great meaſure of happineſſe and proſperitie to the whole nation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:103790:8"/>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:103790:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty. <hi>The bumble</hi> Remonſtrance <hi>and renewed</hi> Petition <hi>of the</hi> Commiſſioners <hi>of the Generall Aſſemblie of the Kirke of</hi> SCOTLAND, <hi>from their meeting at</hi> Edinburgh <hi>the</hi> 2. <hi>day of</hi> June. 1643.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the manifold and preſſing neceſſitie of the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our place and truſt did conſtrain us, in theſe diſtempered and dangerous times, in moſt humble manner, To direct our earneſt ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to your Majeſtie, for ſuch remedies as wee conceive to be moſt fit for us to propone, And being applyed by your Majeſties owne hand, might both for cure and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention prove moſt effectuall: So are we enforced by the ſame neceſſitie growing daily to the greateſt extremitie; In all humilitie and earneſtneſſe, To renew not only our prayers to God, but our Petitions to your Majeſtie. <hi>For Sions ſake can we not hold our peace, and for Jeruſalems ſake we will not reſt, untill the righteouſneſſe thereof go forth as brightneſſe, and the ſalvation thereof as alamp that burneth.</hi> But becauſe in your Majeſties anſwere to our former Petition wee meet with a multitude of prejudices
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103790:9"/>and exceptions againſt us and our humble deſires, wee will crave leave, firſt to remove theſe out of the way: Acknowledging the full expreſſion of them by your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie to be no ſmall favour, and being confident, after we have expreſſed our ſelves in the truth and integritie of our hearts, both to give unto and to receive from your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Juſtice and goodneſſe the greater ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>And firſt, although there bee good reaſon for printing of Anſwers and Replyes, the Petition being before prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet wee acknowledge that your Majeſtie hath juſt cauſe to finde fault with that publiſhing of our Petition in print (which is mentioned in the introduction to your Majeſties anſwer) And if it had been done by our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, counſell or knowledge, we had not only given your Majeſtie juſt provocation, and fallen in an errour contrary to the nature of a Petition, and to the right diſpoſition of Petitioners, but alſo had uſed means contrary to our own ends, in publiſhing a programme of our diffidence of obtaining our deſires, or in giving a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick teſtimony that we were aiming at ſome other thing then what we profeſſed to ſeek, And therefore wee are ſo far from excuſing that forme of doing, that we judge our ſelves to be wronged thereby.</p>
            <p>Another fault much more intollerable is objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us: <hi>The bitterneſſe and ſharpneſſe of ſome expreſsions which may bee interpreted by your Majeſties well affected Subjects not to be ſo agreeable to that regard and reverence which is due to your Majeſties perſon, and the matter it ſelfe to be reprochfull to the honour and conſtitution of that your Majeſties Kingdome.</hi> Whether the matter of the Petition be reproachfull ſhall aferwards in the particulars appear: But for the expreſſions we have examined the whole Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103790:9"/>and can finde no word of that kinde. Wee rather did feare the cenſure of fauning and flattering words, which your Majeſtie may remember were ſometime put upon our ſupplications. Our deſire was to keepe within the bounds of that liberty which beſeemeth the Miniſters of Chriſt, and if any word have eſcaped us which we cannot ſee, it was contrary to our intention: for wee know that we ſhould neither ſpeak evill of dignities nor unreverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto them. The like report hath beene made to your Mejeſtie of our preaching and prayers, but when the de. lators are tryed, they will be found either malicious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us for reproving their faults; Or having no other way of inſinuation, too officious to your Majeſtie, or to others whom they deſire to pleaſe, or ſo blinded with ſelf-love, that they thinke Preachers ſhould ſpeak like Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites; or ſo undiſcerning, that when we profeſſe our deſire to the reformation of Religion in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> we are fanſied by them to preach or pray againſt the King and his royall authoritie. Wee fear God, and honour the King, And have learned not onely to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and the King, but alſo (againſt the old ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtication now revived) betwixt the pictures of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and the images of the falſe gods, craftily inſert in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and know the way how to honour the King with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch a mixture and confuſion. Slowneſſe to beleeve an evill report and the conſtructing of things doubtfull is one of your Majeſties royall praiſes, of which the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters of this Kirk deſire, againſt ſlanders and ſuſpitions to have the experience: which will prove pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for your Majeſties honour and obedience, and our peace and quietneſſe. <hi>As the north winde driveth away rain: So doth an angrie countenance a back biting tongue.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103790:10"/>Righteous lips are the delight of Kings: and they love him that ſpeaketh right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the interpoſing of the Generall Aſſembly of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and our intermedling by commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from them in the affairs of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> We humbly intreat your Majeſtie, to conſider of the reaſons of this our doing. 1. Although the Kirks of one Nation be diſtant in place from the Kirks of another Nation, yet are they united in heart and ſpirit, and are generally but one body and Kirke and muſt as Siſters of one Mother keepe the unitie of the ſpirit in the bond of peace: whence ariſeth the communion of all Gods graces and bleſſings amongſt the Kirks, that they may not only help, comfort and refreſh: but adviſe, admoniſh, exhort, warne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove one another, ſo farre as need requireth and their Chriſtian love and abilitie reacheth. Yet avoiding both ambition and confuſion: there being a coordination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Kirkes of diverſe Nations, but no ſubordination: We have not preſumed to paſſe the limits of this Chriſtian communion: having proceeded by way of charity, and in a <hi>miniſteriall</hi> or rather brotherly manner, not by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or <hi>Magiſterially:</hi> by way of humble ſupplication to your Majeſtie, Declaration to the houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and advice and exhortation to ſuch of our brethren of the Miniſterie as were beſt known unto us: very farre from uſurpation or juriſdiction. 2. Our humble petition to your Majeſtie and our Declaration to the Parliament, were nothing els, but a proſecution of the demand made by the Commiſſioners of this Kingdome, and a preſſing of the anſwer given by your Majeſtie and the Parliament, in the laſt treatie; which filled us with hope of what was then demanded, ſince followed by diverſe Declarations
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103790:10"/>and now again deſired. 3. The experience of the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this Kirk from the doctrine, for me of worſhip and government of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> Doth beget feares of the like hereafter, which maketh our petition to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us a neceſſare meane of ſelf preſervation. 4. Our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements from your Majeſties Letter to the Generall Aſſembly and the Declaration of the houſe of Parliament deſiring them to concur in petitioning your Majeſtie for ſetling one confeſſion of Faith, one directorie of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like worſhip and one Catechiſme in all the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes <hi>as a meane to advance the honour and ſervice of God, enlarge the greatneſſe power and glorie of the King, confirme the peace, ſecuritie and proſperitie of all his good Subjects, make way to the relief and deliverance of the poore afflicted Kirks abroad and to the totall aboliſhing of the uſurpation and tyrannie of Rome.</hi> 5 The paterne wee have of this Chriſtian duty both by word and wryting in the Kirk at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the Kirk at <hi>Antioch,</hi> which was firſt crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the name of Chriſtians, The one of which were <hi>Jewes,</hi> and the other <hi>Gentiles;</hi> And in diverſe other Kirks recorded in Scripture. many Precedents alſo in antiquity before the Kirks did contend for primacy, or knew any preheminence one over another Many examples of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reformed Kirks; And the practiſe of the Kirk of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> diverſe times after the Reformation wryting into <hi>England</hi> againſt the ceremonies and for union againſt the Papiſts and their confederats banded together by the bloudie league of <hi>Trent.</hi> Theſe and the like reaſons wee conceive did ſufficiently authorize us in all that we have done, not as Directors or Judges but as ſupplicants and humble adviſers. <hi>In that day ſhall there be a high way one of</hi> Egypt <hi>into</hi> Aſſyria (from one Kirk and Nation of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103790:11"/>
               <hi>Gentiles</hi> to another) <hi>And the</hi> Egyptians <hi>ſhall ſerve with the</hi> Aſſyrians, <hi>whom the Lord of Hoſtes ſhall bleſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this and the like grounds, have letters been ſent profeſſedly, between ſome godly loyall and peaceable Miniſters of the Kirk of <hi>England</hi> and the Generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly here, and their Commiſſioners: One of the means intended for the good of Religion in both Kingdomes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sects and Shiſmes, admitted and approven by your Majeſties Commiſſioners, in the Generall Aſſembly, and which for the forme of doing is innocent and may bee profitable, unleſſe the matter bee nocent and hurtfull and thereby deſerves cenſure. Wee wiſh we were able by our Letters, Declarations, or Petitions; To reduce all the reformed Kirks to a perfect conformitie, to ſuppreſſe all the Hereſie, Superſtition and Tyrannie of Papiſts, and the Paganiſme of Turkes and Inſidels, and would not doubt of your Majeſties Roy all approbation not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the Lawes ſtanding to the contrarie, and plea's, could be made for their antiquitie, happineſſe and ſtabilitie, Common arguments and collours pretended for every Religion, and of late anſwered to the full in the point of Epiſcopall government, from the verity of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture which is true antiquity and the onely ſolide ground of the happineſſe and ſtabilitie of Religion and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kirk.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners were far from laying upon your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie any Imputation of the <hi>Iriſh</hi>-rebellion beſeeching God to maniſeſt your Sacred Majeſties innocencie to all the world. They made mention of the miſeries of <hi>Ireland</hi> for no other end, but to repreſent the danger of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Kingdomes through the prevailing power of the Popiſh faction, The Britiſh Papiſts at this time being ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103790:11"/>by the ſame ſpirit, working upon the ſame prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, enraged with the ſame furies, breathing out the ſame threatnings and ſlaughter, aiming at the ſame ends, and emboldened with the ſame preſumptions, with the Papiſts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> their confederates. And withall to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent our earneſt deſires for a pacification, that both the armies may bee ſent againſt that horride rebellion, and peace reſtored to all your Majeſties Dominions.</p>
            <p>The expreſſion in our Petition of Unitie in Religion, we have borrowed from the Article in the Treatie accorded unto by your Majeſtie; from the Declarations of the Parliament; and from the Generall Aſſemblie: By which is meaned no other thing but one Confeſſion of Faith, one common directorie for worſhip, and one Gate chiſme. The Papiſts may know that the true Kirk in all ages hath been troubled with differences and contentions as great as any now againſt the reformed Kirks, which many of the godly have lamented and ſtudied to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and (as it was written of ſome hereticks of old) <hi>They themſelves ſacrifice in ſchiſme and diſſention, and greet the world with the name of peace, whom they drive from the peace of their ſalvation.</hi> They therefore cannot hence au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize their ſcandall againſt the reformation: yet the ſmalleſt differences of practiſe and diverſitie of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, are matter of ſtrife to the contentious, of hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of edification to the ignorant, of ſtumbling to the weake, and of grief to the godly, when thereby they ſee againſt religious Unitie and Chriſtian love, the bowels of the Kirk rent aſſunder, and people ſcandalouſly divided in ſome parts of the worſhip of God: All which evil, might be perfectly cured in all your Majeſties dominions the mouthes of Papiſts ſcopped, ſchiſme and ſeparation
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103790:12"/>hereafter prevented, and the face of the Kirke filled with true beautie and ſplendor to your Majeſties greater glory and the greater terrour of all your enemies, by this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and never enough deſired Unitie in Religion: Without which tender conſciences being freed from conſtraine may bee in ſome degree eaſed by your Majeſtie, but ſhall never have reſt and be ſatisfied; nor ſhall the rent of the Kirk ariſing from different or contrary practiſes be cured, but ſhall from time to time increaſe.</p>
            <p>Concerning uniformity in Kirk government, our hopes thereof and of the unitie of Religion grounded upon the Article of the Treatie, made this Kirk and Kingdome to enter into the more ſtrict amitie and friendſhip with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And that the amitie and friendſhip builded upon ſuch a foundation might be the more firme and durable, they have ſince preſſed the ſame by their Petitions and Declarations, in all humilitie and love without any bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of expreſſion: Onely they have declared the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Kirk by Aſſemblies in their ſtrong and beautifull order and ſubordination to bee by divine right, and that as Prelacie is confeſſed in this your Majeſties an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to be by the rule of humane policie, ſo to bee almoſt univerſally acknowledged by the Prelates themſelves and their adherents to be but a humane inſtitution, introduced by humane reaſon, and ſetled by humane law and cuſtom, for ſuppoſed conveniencie; which therefore by humane authoritie, without wronging any mans conſcience, may be altered and aboliſhed upon ſo great a neceſſity, as is, a heartie conjunction of all the reformed Kirks, a firme and well grounded peace between the two Kingdomes, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly divided in themſelves and betwixt themſelves by this partition wall, and a perfect Union of the two Kirks
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103790:12"/>in the two Nations; which although by the providence of God in one Iſland, and under one Monarch, yet ever ſince the Reformation have been at greater difference in the point of Kirk government (which in all places hath a powerfull influence upon all the parts of Religion) then any other reformed Kirks, although in nations at greateſt diſtance and under diverſe Princes. Papacie is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt cauſe of ſchiſme in the Chriſtian Kirk, and Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie deviſed by man to bee a cure, the greateſt cauſe of ſchiſme in the reformed Kirks.</p>
            <p>As the mutuall relation and conjunction of true Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſticall and Civill government is a corroboration of both, ſo do we conceive that both are much weakened in their proper functions by that intermixture of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall government with the Civill State. And as wee know the principles of Prelacie to be Popiſh, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the principles of Reformation: So have we rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to beleeve, That ſuch an intermixture is not for your Majeſties honour, while they maintain and profeſſe that Monarchie cannot ſubſiſt without Prelacie: And that Prelacie had not been caſt out of the Parliament if it had been profitable there; And thought fit to bee altogether aboliſhed, if it had not been an unprofitable burthen to the Kingdome, and pernicious to the civill State and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, As is contained more fully in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of both Houſes of Parliament to the Generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie.</p>
            <p>The following of humane inventions, without and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scripture and the ambition and covetouſneſſe of Kirkmen were obſerved of old to bee the corruptions which made many to call upon the Pope and the chiefe guides of the Kirke at that time for a reformation: but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103790:13"/>all in vaine, for that had been their own ruine, to which in humane reaſon, they would never willingly have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented. That upon the ſame cauſes and corruptions there is a neceſſitie of the reformation of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> Is as unanimouſly confeſſed, as it is univerſally acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that it is unlikely if not impoſſible; to be obtained in the regulate and ordinarie way: Upon the reaſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt afterward in your Majeſties anſwer. <hi>Becauſe in the common and ordinary way the paſsion or intereſt of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar men will impoſe upon the publict:</hi> For what greater pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat intereſt then benefits and dignities? Who more inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſed in theſe then Biſhops, Deans, Arch. deacons and ſuch ordinary members of the convocation? And ho can be more ſueyed and by aſſed with paſſion then ſuch as have this intereſt? Whether this bee applyable to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whoſe places and dignities are uncontroverted and unqueſtionable, it is not for us to judge: but this we know when the corruptions of the Kirk are grown to ſuch an height, that ſhe can neither beare her diſeaſes, nor endure the remedies, it is the dutie of the magiſtrat and civill au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, by the advice of the more ſound and ſincere part of the Kirke and Miniſtrie, to endeavoure a reformation, ſince no reformation, worthie of that name, can be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from the corrupt Clergie, nor hath at any time Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion been that way in any tolerable meaſure reformed: When the evils are extraordinary, the remedies muſt bee other then ordinary. Scripture, reaſon and experience of the Kirk teach in ſuch an exigence of reformation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamitie of debates and contentions, to call a Synod of the beſt Divines, beſt acquainted with the will of God in Scripture freeſt of humane inventions and innovations, and farreſt from pride and avarice; which are the evils to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103790:13"/>be purged out, and for afterward prevented; And who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Sects and Shiſmes unfainedly ſeek the peace and unitie of the Kirke which by all good meanes both for it ſelfe and for the truthes ſake is to bee procured and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. When by this remedie faithfully applyed and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with prayers and teares of repentance; the worſhip of God and the government of the Kirk are ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, not after the rules of humane policie but according to Scripture, there is hope that God will end his contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie with <hi>England</hi> and bliſſe the treaties of peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your Majeſtie and your Parliament; which is now our humble deſire and when it commeth to paſſe ſhall be the univerſall rejoycing of all your good people.</p>
            <p>We ſhould bee not only unchriſtian but diſloyall and unnaturall, if we were not affected and afflicted with your Majeſties many ſufferings and the troubles of your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and did not heartily wiſh that your Majeſtie were preſent in your parliam. aſſembled in the moſt peaceable and Parliamentary way, to your Ma. greater glorie and their greater ſtrengthening for the good of the Kingdom. For the preſent the houſes of Parliament have profeſſed in their Declaration to the Generall Aſſembly, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and willingneſſe to ſettle ſuch a reformation of the Kirk; as ſhall be moſt agreeable to the word of God, and moſt apt to procure and conſerve an happy union with the Kirke of <hi>Scotland</hi> in a peaceable and Parliamentary way; And have paſſed their bills in both houſes without contradiction againſt Epiſcopall government, and offered them to your Majeſtie for obtaining your Royall conſent This is the peaceable and Parliamentary way meant by us and mentioned in our Petition, which we truſt can give your Majeſtie no juſt offence.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:103790:14"/>
            <p>Although the Miniſters of the Goſpel have authority in ſome caſes to preach and write not only exhortations and bleſſings but alſo threats and ſentences of judgement againſt Kings and Kingdomes, which howſoever they be bitter and unpleaſant for the preſent (and therefore ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome miniſtred to Princes) may prove very profitable and cordiall afterward: Many had periſhed in their ſinnes if it had not been told them that they were to periſh; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are the wounds of a friend, but the kiſſes of an enemy are deceitfull: and hee that rebuketh, afterwards ſhall finde more favour then he that flattereth with the tongue Yet upon good reaſon have we abſtained from this ſtrain of denuncing of judgement againſt your Majeſtie, having onely from the conſcience of our duty in anguiſh of our ſoules, faithfully repreſented the duty and danger with our earneſt deprecation of the wrath not onely now incumbent, but yet ſeven times more imminent to your Kingdomes, which wee daily more and more apprehend; ſhall enſue, unles by a through reformation of Religion and manners it be timeouſly prevented. By this our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we have delivered our own ſoules and endeavoured to deliver your Majeſtie and your Dominions from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and future judgements, which both love and feare conſtraine us now againe; To entreat your Majeſtie to hearken unto.</p>
            <p>As wee cannot deny, but do reverently acknowledge the influence of many and great bleſſings from heaven upon the reigne of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and your Majeſties father of bleſſed memorie: So do we not doubt but your Majeſtie in your Chriſtian and Royall wiſedome will conſider: that the ſupreame providence which hath ſet your Majeſtie after them upon the throne, hath appointed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103790:14"/>a time for every action. <hi>A wiſe mans heart diſcerneth both time and judgement,</hi> and where it is not diſcerned, <hi>the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of man,</hi> wreſtling with invincible providence, <hi>is great upon him.</hi> The many bleſſings upon the Kings of <hi>Egypt, Babylon</hi> and other Princes, were interrupted in the time of their ſucceſſours, which oppoſed the deliverance of the people of God from the <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage, the <hi>Babylonian</hi> captivitie, the fooliſhneſſe of <hi>Paganiſme</hi> and the tyrannie of Poperie, when the time of their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was come. Many of the godly before your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties reigne have deſired and ſupplicated the Parliament for a reformation but the deſires were never ſo univerſall as now; Prelacie never ſo inſolent nor the evils thereof ſo well known and ſo deeply felt; nor was it ever voted out of the Parliament, nor agreed in Parliament to be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Kirk; nor ſtood meerly upon the Royall conſent of the King, till this time. <hi>Arminianiſme</hi> hath entered, Papiſtrie hath encreaſed, Sectaries have multiplied, ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings have abounded, Tender conſciences diſquieted with old and new ceremonies, much more of late then before that all eyes may ſee how many things concurre now to make a neceſſitie of reformation. It is the never dying ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your Majeſties late Progenitors above others that were before them that they did begin, continue and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve reformation, and ſhall bee your Majeſties greateſt and immortall glorie to perfite it, with <hi>Joſiah</hi> leaving no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to imped or obſcure the glorie of God: An happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which the people of God in this Iland have long waited for, which God calleth for at your hands and we truſt hath reſerved for our times, as a ſpeciall and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable honour to your Majeſtie above the beſt princes, and matter of joy to your people above all other in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:103790:15"/>
            <p>As the continuall comfort and daily ſenſe of the ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable benefit of the reformation of this Kirk in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and government ſhould ſtir up our hearts, to the love of God, whoſe hand principally did bring it about, in a way full of marvels and full of mercies, And thankfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to your Majeſtie whom wee look upon not as a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked aſſenter unto alterations, but as a prime inſtrument of ſetling a bleſſed reformation in this Kirke; So doeth the ſame comfort and ſenſe excite in us a fear to loſſe that which we ſo much love in a way wherein it hath rune ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard before. Our feares are not counterfeit to bring any deſigne of our own, nor politick or created in us by the authoritie of any aſſertion of others to bring any deſigne of theirs to paſſe, nor panick or maginarie to torment our ſelves without cauſe; But are true and reall, grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reaſon which teacheth to beware of contagion in ſo neer a vicinitie and where there is ſo frequent commerce and converſing, upon by paſt experience of evils from <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Prelacie ever ſince the beginning of reformation and upon preſent and daily taſting of the fruits which partly of its own corrupt nature, and partly through the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of men, It hath brought forth and fomented. And though the Petitioners cannot judge nor ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedle with queſtions about your Majeſties and the Parliaments power, yet may they well profeſſe from that which every one may underſtand that the denying of the people their earneſt deſires may quench that fervour of affection which is due from a people to their Prince.</p>
            <p>Whether the generality of the Nation deſireth a change of Kirk government, cannot bee better knowne then by the deſires and Propoſitions of the repreſentative hodie of the Kingdome, nor can it bee better defyned what go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103790:15"/>ſhall be eſtabliſhed than in a Synod of learned and godly Divines. Our part is to wiſh the patterne is Scripture and the example of the beſt Reformed Kirks to be followed, and to pray that God by his Spirit may lead them into all truth: being confident that reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion having begun by your Majeſties authoritie at the head and chiefeſt parts, all ſectaries, and all the inferiour mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers may be quickly by a Synod brought to ſuch order as may conſiſt with truth and with the peace of the Kirk.</p>
            <p>It was far from our intentions by the generall expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Petition againſt Papiſts, To charge your Ma. with complyance and favour to their opinions. We do from our hearts bleſſe God for all that your Majeſtie hath done both here and in England againſt them, and for ſo free and ample a teſtimonie of your Majeſties deſires of the Queenes converſion. Jealouſies of that kinde, and hopes in the hearts of ſuch as are popiſhly affected, of their prevailing power, proceed from the power of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in Ireland, the preſent poſture of Papiſts armed about your Majeſtie in this dangerous time of combuſtion in England, and that for ſo long a time through the conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence or complyance of the Miniſters of eſtate, lawes, have not been execute againſt them, nor any means at all uſed for the Queenes converſion. A neceſſary and eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all duty, from which no oath to the contrary can more give diſpenſation, then any oath of old or late, publick or private, can binde your Majeſtie to maintaine Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie or any corruption in the worſhippe of God, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Kirk, when God by his word giveth light and by his providence calleth for a Reformation. All which had need to be ſeriouſly and tymouſly conſidered. And if the Papiſts be not ſpeedily diſarmed, the danger is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103790:16"/>that both in their owne project, and upon the hearing of your Majeſties Declaration to diſarme them, when there ſhall bee no more uſe of their ſervice, they band together and bend all their wits againſt a Pacification, till by their gathering and growing to greater ſtrength, they be able to plead in equall termes for themſelves, for their ſhare in the places and honours of the Kingdome, at leſt for peace and tolleration, as a reward of all their paines, charges and hazards, pretended to bee for your Majeſties honour and ſafety, but really intended for themſelves and their ſuperſtition. We cannot conceive that loyaltie can be without allegeance, or that Papiſts refuſing to take the oath of allegeance, do fight in loyaltie and allegeance to your Majeſtie, but for their own ends, nor can it bee ſafe for Proteſtants to truſt them upon the principles of their profeſſion, in any whether inteſtine or forraigne warre. In the time of the greateſt forraigne invaſion year 88. It was not thought ſafe to arme the Papiſts in defence of the Kingdome. We did not take notice of Papiſts in the other armie, in our Petition to your Majeſtie, but did in our Declaration to the Parliament, that although they had profeſſed in their Declarations that they had no knowne Papiſts in their Armie, yet if any were found to be, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired they might in like manner be disbanded. Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, and other ſectaries which are the fruits of Prelacie one way as Papiſts are another, are neither ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily knowne as Papiſts nor ſo much to be feared: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be enemies to Religion and to the peace of the Kirk, we know not whether they have been ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable that the law hath taken ſo far notice of them as to diſarme them.</p>
            <p>We have ſo ſincerely and from the inward of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103790:16"/>with our hearts and hands lifted up to the moſt high God the ſearcher of hearts, ſworne the care of the ſafty of your Majeſties perſon, and of your greatneſſe and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, which we have alſo witneſſed in our Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Houſes of Parliament, that our hearts within us were wounded when we did heare of the danger your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties perſon was in the 23 of October. And as wee doe with the Houſes of Parliament (as is expreſſed in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration) rejoyce and heartily praiſe God for your ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, So do we not ceaſe to pray for your Majeſties preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in the midſt of ſo many dangers, and for a ſpeedy deliverance by a happie peace, which we truſt ſhall burie that black and unnaturall day ſo unhappie and dangerous both to you: Majeſtie and your people in eternall oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, And therefore not to be paralelled by us with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paralelled plot of the 5 of Novem. never to be forgoten.</p>
            <p>We have detained your Majeſtie longer then your great affairs of governing Kingdomes in the time of war could well permit, but not ſo long as the charge committed to us by the Generall Aſſemblie, and the importance of our Petition, which is of religious and publick concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth require. The cry me of bitterneſſe and want of reverence to your Majeſtie, the challenge of uſurpation, the aſperſion of ſo much and manifold miſtaking, wee would bear the more patiently if we were to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as privat and particular perſons, and not as Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of publick truſt: And yet do bear the more pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, becauſe we take them (and in this no man ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us that we are miſtaken) to proceed from the pen of the writer, and not from your Majeſties juſtice and goodneſſe, unto which wee are bold to appeall from his unjuſt cenſure, and from ſuch ſlanderous tongues and pens
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103790:17"/>as by traducing the preaching and praiers of the miniſtery here of diſloyaltie or ſedition, do much wrong us, your Majeſtie much more, and truth and peace moſt of all. Your Majeſtie in your wiſedome will conſider what ſuch Sycophants are ſeeking, and in your juſtice will rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve our publick teſtimonie, in things beſt known to our ſelves and to our ordinarie hearers, then any private infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation flowing from the malice of ſome, or the weakenes of others. And now in your royall goodneſſe will bee graciouſly pleaſed to ſuffer us your Maieſties moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and faithfull Subjects to fall downe at your feet, and with all earneſtneſſe to renew our Petition, eſpecially that of Unitie in Religion, and uniformitie of Kirk Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all your Majeſties Dominions, which wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be principally intended by divine Providence in theſe unhappie diſtractions and troubles of your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Kingdomes; And to this effect for ſuch an Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Aſſemblie, as hath been formerly deſcribed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired: A mean ſo pious, ſo juſt and ſo ordinarie in ſuch caſes as malice itſelfe can have no colour to object againſt your Majeſtie for uſing it. And which ſhall ſpeedily bring on a firme and well grounded peace, and with peace all other bleſſings ſpirituall and temporall upon your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and your Kingdomes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker. <hi>Cl: Commiſs. Gen. Aſſ.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
